Guide to the Mary Sheldon Barnes Pacific Slope Collection, 1769-1898
Mary Sheldon Barnes Pacific Slope Collection,
1769-1898
Special Collections M0067
Barnes, Mary Sheldon
1 linear foot
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections.
Letters, reminiscences, interviews, and term papers written for and collected by Mary Sheldon Barnes and her students in Pacific Slope history. Includes manuscripts of William B. Ide and others on the Bear Flag Revolt; a letter by Jessie Fremont; and other materials pertaining to California mining and early life in the Pacific states.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary Sheldon Barnes.
Provenance
Collected by Mary Sheldon Barnes and other Stanford faculty and students (1892-1896).
Scope and Contents Note
This collection includes term papers, theses, interviews, letters, and reminiscences written and collected for various courses at Stanford University pertaining to the Pacific States. Original papers of particular interest deal with the Bear Flag Revolt and California mining. The collection also includes a letter by Jessie B. Fremont; and Moses Shallenberger letters, along with a transcript of an interview giving his account of the journey to California in 1844.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Barnes, Mary Sheldon, 1850-1898.; Boggs, William M.; Cooper, Joseph Wright.; Easterby, Anthony Y.; Fremont, Jessie Benton, 1824-1902.; Hittell, Theodore Henry, 1830-1917.; Ide, William B.; Vasquez, Don Pablo.; New Coso Mining Co. (Calif.); Bear Flag Revolt, 1846.; Miners--California.; Overland journeys to the Pacific.; Sheep--California.; California--History--1846-1850.; Napa (Calif.); Oregon--History.; San Benito (Calif.); Sonoma (Calif.)
Collection Contents
- Pacific Slopes Manuscripts Volume 1
  - Enquiry into the route of the expedition of Governor Portola, in 1769 from their camp near Point Ano Nuevo to their camp in the San Francisquito Creek. Made by Mary Sheldon Barnes, Clark Hetherington, Henry D. Sheldon, and John Gregory, Jr., all of Stanford University, 1893, Item 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of the missions of upper California with dates of foundtion and references, by Nellie McCaughan., Item 2; Typewritten. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution adopted by a pioneer train of 1849 in crossing the continent, contributed by A. R. Cotton., Item 3; Typewritten. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bibliography of Santa Clara County prepared by Myron A. Folsom., Item 4; Typewritten. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The early settlement of California by George H. Hazzard, including descriptions of many of the different kinds of settlements outside of the missions made before 1850 and a complete list of the mining towns founded immediately after the gold discovery., Item 5; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Settlements of Utah and Nevada, by Sam Platt., Item 6; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter of Lt. Tunis Augustus Craven of February, 1847 aboard the U. S. S. Dale at sea pertaining to California in general and the war in California., Item 7; Partially handwritten and partially typed. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Outline history of the Pacific Slope, by Prof. M. S. Barnes. Discovery and nomenclature of the principle rivers, bays, ports, and islands on the coast of California, by John M. Gregory, Jr., Item 8; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chilean affair of 1891-1893, by Robert D. MacFarland., Item 9; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A chronological list of the discoverers and explorers of the Oregon country, by W. C. Hazzard., Item 10; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - List of exploration in California to 1848, by Delos Magee., Item 11; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Russian discoveries and settlements in Alaska., Item 12; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Spanish and Mexican land grants, by W. E. Stuart., Item 13; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Historical brief by R. C. Hopkins pertaining to inducements by Spain to foreign settlers in the new world, obtained by W. E. Stuart., Item 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Settlements in the Oregon Country to 1850 / by J. Foster Hidden, Item 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Pacific Slopes Manucripts Volume 3
  - Spanishtown and along shore in California days, by Don Pablo Vasquez., Item 1; Printed in the Sequoia. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Spanishtown and along shore in California days, by Don Pablo Vasquez., Item 2; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The story of the San Pablo Rancho, by John Francis Sheehan, Jr., Item 3; Published. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Robles Rancheria, mound excavation in California., Item 4; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Politics in California, 1848 to 1894, by H. E. Cox, Item 5; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ancient Mexico as seen by Cortes and Bernal Diaz, by Edith M. Jordan., Item 6; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Easterby's account of the founding of Fresno, dictated to G. A. Clark; along with a letter from Easterby regarding the account., Item 7; Typewritten and handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mormons in California, by William M. Boggs., Item 8; Letter. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bent's Fort by William M. Boggs; drawn from memory fifty years after Boggs was in the fort with accompanying letters., Item 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notes from Sonoma and Napa interviews, including some information about the Donner party., Item 10; Typewritten and handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Establishment of the Greek-Russian Church of San Francisco, by Clara Vostrofsky from interviews., Item 11; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The present condition of the California Missions, December 1894, by Rose Patterson., Item 12; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Report upon the Apache Indians, by R. D. McFarland., Item 13; Handwritten. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Reminiscences of overland journey to California in 1844 given by Mrs. Judge Wallace of Mayfield., Item 14; Typewritten. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Manuscript of one of the unemployed of 1894, obtained by Joseph Dixon., Item 15; Handwritten original and typed copy. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Oregon bibliographies., Item 16; Typewritten. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Graph and map (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Pacific Slopes Manuscripts Volume 4
  - Notes on early California industries by J. W. Cooper of Santa Barbara and John R. Coe of Napa, along with letters and reminiscences. Cooper claims to have been with the first drive of sheep to California. Coe describes farming in some detail., 1
  - Copy of a letter written home by Dr. Benjamin Cory from the gold fields in 1848., 2
  - Letter on the Hudson Bay Company by George H. Tinkham., 3
  - Letter from the Hawaiian Islands written by a resident in 1895., 4; Handwritten.
  - Syllabus of course given at the U. of Washington on the history of the northwest coast, 1896., 5; Mimeographed.
  - Bibliography of the Bear Flag Revolt, by Minnie Coulter, along with letters from William M. Boggs, Theodore H. Hittell and Moses Schallenberger evaluating the currently available sources on California history, 1897., 6; Typewritten and handwritten.
  - Notes of Mr. Horatio N. Rust, from his personal observation of pottery making, fire making, and weaving among the Moquis of Arizona., 7; Typewritten.
  - Some phases of Alaskan government; a study from original sources and authorities, by F. S. Howard, 1896., 8; Handwritten.
  - Early land system in Oregon, by Nelly M. Hill, 1895., 9; Clipping of published version and original manuscript.
  - Letter from Don Pablo Vasquez of Spanishtown, describing the process of making adobe bricks, 1896., 10; Handwritten.
  - Bolitas of the New Coso Mining Company, Darwin City, Inyo County, with letter from E. S. Campbell to Mrs. David Starr Jordan explaining the use of scrip to pay the miners, 1895., 11; Typescript copy of letter and original pieces of scrip.
  - Letters from William M. Boggs, with sketches, describing buffalo hunting on the plains, 1895., 12; Handwritten.
  - Copies of reports of miners meetings, Smith Flat District and Poverty Hill, late 1850s, transcribed by O. Hopkins, 1896., 13; Typewritten.
  - Autographed letter of Mrs. Jessie Fremont in regard to the conquest of California, March 14, 1895., 14; Handwritten.
  - Letters of Dr. Samuel J. Parker relative to statements made in his manuscript on the Oregon Missions, 1896-1898., 15; Handwritten.
  - Bibliography of Alaskan missions prepared by Lucy Allabach., 16; Handwritten.
  - Chronology of Russian America by Katherine A. Chandler, 1897., 17; Handwritten.
  - The Great Northern Railway System, a thesis by F. S. Howard, 1897., 18; Typewritten.
  - References for California settlement before 1849, by Mary Leddy, 1897., 19; Handwritten.
  - The rediscovery of Monterey and the founding of San Carlos Mission, [translated by Elinor A. Smith] from "The Historical Relation of the Life and Apostolic Labors of the Venerable Father Fray Junipero Serra.. ." by Rev. Father L. F. F. Palou, 1897., 20; Typewritten.
  - The rediscovery of Monterey and the founding of San Carlos Mission, translated from Vol. ii of "Information Concerning New California" written by Rev. Father F. F. Palou, by Elinor A. Smith, 1897., 21; Typewritten.
  - Partial copy of William Carey Jones' report on land titles in California made for the U. S. Government in 1849., 22; Typewritten.
  - Great Northern Railway map; transcontinental route for passenger and freight, 1896., 23; Printed.
- Pacific Slopes Manuscripts Volume 5
  - The Bear Flag Revolt as related by William B. Ide in a manuscript presented to the L. S. J. U. by Mrs. Sarah B. Ide Healy, his daughter, in 1893, with an accompanying letter., 1; Handwritten.
  - The Bear Flag Revolt as related by Mr. William Baldridge and other participants still residing in Napa Valley to Mrs. Mary Sheldon Barnes, 1892-1893; along with Mr. Baldridge's manuscript account of the Bear Flag Revolt, ca. 1894., 2; Typewritten and handwritten.
- Maps and Drawings
  - Two hand drawn maps showing Indian trails of San Mateo County by McClellan with the assistance of Pedro Evancio (the last Indian survivor of Dolores Mission), 1895. (Folder 1)
  - Three drawings by William M. Boggs. (Folder 2)
  - Map tracings, including a manuscript map by Pedro Evancio. (Box 1)